[Music]
a series of articles published in the
annals of internal medicine recommending
people just keep eating their meat was
decried by nutrition researchers as
irresponsible and unethical a travesty
of science and assault on public health
and the most egregious abusive evidence
that they had ever seen
there were calls for retraction even
before it was published from eminent
public health leaders from a former u.s
surgeon general former president of the
american college of cardiology and the
directors of preventive medicine and
nutrition institutes from harvard yale
tufts and stanford
in my last video i explained the how
the method by which they manipulated the
science but never really got to the why
i mean the lead authors similar attempt
to discredit the sugar guidelines was
explicitly paid for by an industry front
group funded by the likes of coca-cola
dr pepper
mars candy bars and pepsi
but if you look at the meat paper at the
panelists declared conflicts of interest
they all say they didn't have any
including the lead author who was
involved in the sugar study whose
primary funder wasn't just representing
big soda and candy but the likes of
mcdonald's and one of the largest meat
packers in the world
yet johnston didn't disclose that as a
potential conflict of interest when he
switched from exonerating sugar to
exonerating meat
what did he have to say for himself
even though the sugar study was
published in 2016 he got the money for
it in 2015 outside of the three-year
mandatory disclosure window
this is the same guy who said the
industry front group had no role in
writing their paper until the associated
press revealed the truth and the journal
had to publish a correction
but johnston doubled down this time
saying it is tenuous at best to suggest
that his earlier work on sugar had any
influence on how his team made the new
meat recommendations the important thing
is we have no relationship with the meat
industry
oh
really
a few months later
the truth came out correction in the
so-called nutrirex panel meat
recommendations oops
bradley johnson failed to indicate he
had gotten a grant from texas a m
agrilife which gets millions of dollars
a year from the meat industry to do
things like run beef boot camp or
espouse the health benefits of beef
brisket or promote the celebration of
national bacon day
after all texas a m agrilife serves pork
producers to improve pork producer
profitability
this is the group that not only gave
doctor no relationship with the meat
industry johnston a direct grant for
over 75 grand
but they officially joined the whole
nutrex consortium to provide as dr
johnston explained
generous support to impact
nutrition-related decision-making and
policy in north america and beyond
yet none of this was disclosed in the
paper
no even potential conflict of interest
yet they had formed a partnership with
an arm of texas a m partially funded by
the beef industry to the tunes of
millions a year from the beef industry
alone
oops
in fact patrick stover mr no conflicts
of interest
is
the director of agrilife and a month
before the meet paper was published
bradley johnson was offered and accepted
a tenured position at texas a m agrilife
was already working for them when it was
published but didn't think to mention it
so when the annals initially sent out a
press release which they later corrected
saying no need to reduce red or
processed meat consumption for good
health they may have been simply acting
as a mouthpiece for meat industry
propaganda the pseudoscience presented
in the annals meat papers appears to
have been written solely to create doubt
and confusion in the wider population
the misleading recommendations were not
intended to convince scientists who
clearly understand the nature of the
relationship between meat and health and
for that matter sugar and health the
pseudoscience is presented solely to
create doubt and confusion in the wider
population
frankly
industry will do what it needs to do to
push as much of its product into the
world as it can and so will do what it
needs to do to obfuscate the
relationship between its products and
human and planetary health
they've done it with tobacco fossil
fuels monsanto's roundup sugar and now
meat
[Music]
you